<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Martini Force Field Initiative</title>
<link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/</link>
<atom:link href="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://cgmartini.nl/images/martini.gif</url>
<title>Martini Force Field Initiative</title>
<link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.7.33</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A systematic approach to parameterization of disaccharides for the Martini 3 coarse-grained force-field</title>
  <dc:creator>Astrid F Brandner, Iain PS Smith, Siewert J Marrink, Paulo CT Souza, and Syma Khalid</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brandner2025_Disaccharides.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brandner, A. F., Smith, I. P., Marrink, S. J., Souza, P. C., &amp; Khalid, S. (2025). Systematic Approach to Parametrization of Disaccharides for the Martini 3 Coarse-Grained Force Field. Journal of chemical information and modeling.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Sugars are ubiquitous in biology; they occur in all kingdoms of life. Despite their prevalence, they have often been somewhat neglected in studies of structure–dynamics–function relationships of macromolecules to which they are attached, with the exception of nucleic acids. This is largely due to the inherent difficulties of not only studying the conformational dynamics of sugars using experimental methods but indeed also resolving their static structures. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations offer a route to the prediction of conformational ensembles and the time-dependent behavior of sugars and glycosylated macromolecules. However, at the all-atom level of detail, MD simulations are often too computationally demanding to allow a systematic investigation of molecular interactions in systems of interest. To overcome this, large scale simulations of complex biological systems have profited from advances in coarse-grained (CG) simulations. Perhaps the most widely used CG force field for biomolecular simulations is Martini. Here, we present a parameter set for glucose- and mannose-based disaccharides for Martini 3. The generation of the CG parameters from atomistic trajectories is automated as fully as possible, and where not possible, we provide details of the protocol used for manual intervention.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Glycans</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brandner2025_Disaccharides.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An integrative modelling approach to the mitochondrial cristae</title>
  <dc:creator>Chelsea M. Brown, Marieke S. S. Westendorp, Rubi Zarmiento-Garcia, Jan A. Stevens, Bart M. H. Bruininks, Sarah L. Rouse, Siewert J. Marrink &amp; Tsjerk A. Wassenaar </dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brown2025_Cristae.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brown, C. M., Westendorp, M. S., Zarmiento-Garcia, R., Stevens, J. A., Bruininks, B. M., Rouse, S. L., Marrink, S.J. &amp; Wassenaar, T. A. (2025). An integrative modelling approach to the mitochondrial cristae. Communications Biology, 8(1), 972.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Mitochondria are implicated in many cellular functions such as energy production and apoptosis but also disease pathogenesis. To effectively perform these roles, the mitochondrial inner membrane has invaginations known as cristae that dramatically increase the surface area. This works to provide more space for membrane proteins that are essential to the roles of mitochondria. While separate components of this have been studied computationally, it remains a challenge to combine elements into an overall model. Here, we present a comprehensive model of a crista junction from a human mitochondrion and the accompanying workflow to construct it. Our coarse-grained representation of a crista shows how various experimentally determined features of organelles can be combined with molecular modelling to give insights into the interactions and dynamics of complicated biological systems. This work is presented as an initial ‘living’ model for this system, intended to be built upon and improved as our understanding, methodology and resources develop.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brown2025_Cristae.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GōMartini 3: From large conformational changes in proteins to environmental bias corrections</title>
  <dc:creator>Paulo CT Souza, Luis P Borges Araujo, Chris Brasnett, Rodrigo A Moreira, Fabian Grunewald, Peter Park, Liguo Wang, Hafez Razmazma, Ana C Borges-Araujo, Luis F Cofas-Vargas, Luca Monticelli, Raul Mera-Adasme, Manuel N Melo, Sangwook Wu, Siewert J Marrink, Adolfo B Poma, and Sebastian Thallmair</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Souza2025_GoMartini.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Souza, P. C., Borges-Araújo, L., Brasnett, C., Moreira, R. A., Grünewald, F., Park, P., … &amp; Thallmair, S. (2025). GōMartini 3: from large conformational changes in proteins to environmental bias corrections. Nature Communications, 16(1), 4051.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Coarse-grained modeling has become an important tool to supplement experimental measurements, allowing access to spatio-temporal scales beyond all-atom based approaches. The GōMartini model combines structure- and physics-based coarse-grained approaches, balancing computational efficiency and accurate representation of protein dynamics with the capabilities of studying proteins in different biological environments. This paper introduces an enhanced GōMartini model, which combines a virtual-site implementation of Gō models with Martini 3. The implementation has been extensively tested by the community since the release of the reparametrized version of Martini. This work demonstrates the capabilities of the model in diverse case studies, ranging from protein-membrane binding to protein-ligand interactions and AFM force profile calculations. The model is also versatile, as it can address recent inaccuracies reported in the Martini protein model. Lastly, the paper discusses the advantages, limitations, and future perspectives of the Martini 3 protein model and its combination with Gō models.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Forcefield</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Souza2025_GoMartini.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hexokinase-I directly binds to a charged membrane-buried glutamate of mitochondrial VDAC1 and VDAC2</title>
  <dc:creator>Sebastian Bieker, Michael Timme, Nils Woge, Dina G Hassan, Chelsea M Brown, Siewert J Marrink, Manuel N Melo, and Joost CM Holthuis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Bieker2025_Hexokinase1VDAC.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Bieker, S., Timme, M., Woge, N., Hassan, D. G., Brown, C. M., Marrink, S. J., … &amp; Holthuis, J. C. (2025). Hexokinase-I directly binds to a charged membrane-buried glutamate of mitochondrial VDAC1 and VDAC2. Communications biology, 8(1), 212.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Binding of hexokinase HKI to mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion channels (VDACs) has far-reaching physiological implications. However, the structural basis of this interaction is unclear. Combining computer simulations with experiments in cells, we here show that complex assembly relies on intimate contacts between the N-terminal α-helix of HKI and a charged membrane-buried glutamate on the outer wall of VDAC1 and VDAC2. Protonation of this residue blocks complex formation in silico while acidification of the cytosol causes a reversable release of HKI from mitochondria. Membrane insertion of HKI occurs adjacent to the bilayer-facing glutamate where a pair of polar channel residues mediates a marked thinning of the cytosolic leaflet. Disrupting the membrane thinning capacity of VDAC1 dramatically impairs its ability to bind HKI in silico and in cells. Our data reveal key topological and mechanistic insights into HKI-VDAC complex assembly that may benefit the development of therapeutics to counter pathogenic imbalances in this process.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>pH</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Bieker2025_Hexokinase1VDAC.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Insight into the Self-Assembly Behaviors of Per-and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances Using a Computational Microscope</title>
  <dc:creator>Bei Yan, Riccardo Alessandri, Siewert J Marrink, Linda S Lee, and Jinxia Liu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Yan2025_Polyfloroalkyl.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Yan, B., Alessandri, R., Marrink, S. J., Lee, L. S., &amp; Liu, J. (2025). Insight into the Self-Assembly Behaviors of Per-and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances Using a “Computational Microscope”. Environmental Science &amp; Technology Letters, 12(5), 626-631.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Aqueous film-forming foams (AFFFs) have been extensively used for firefighting, contributing to environmental contamination with per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). Most PFAS in AFFFs are fluorosurfactants, known to self-assemble into large supramolecular assemblies in the field of physical chemistry; however, the application of this phenomenon to understanding environmental fate has not been studied. We hypothesize that self-assembled PFAS likely enhance the long-term retention of PFAS in subsurface environments, acting as a continuous source of dissolved PFAS. Thus, characterizing these self-assemblies and understanding their aggregation dynamics are crucial for assessing the fate and transport of PFAS. Despite the utility of molecular dynamics (MD) simulation in studying surfactant behaviors, fluorosurfactants have been underexplored due to the lack of force field parameters. In this study, we developed coarse-grained (CG) force field parameters for fluorosurfactants based on the Martini 3 model and performed CG-MD simulations. These “computational microscope” simulations reveal the self-assembly behavior of selected PFAS, aligning with experimental cryo-transmission electron microscopy observations and providing mechanistic insights. Our work sheds light on the evolution of solvated PFAS self-assemblies over time and space. The CG-MD simulation can particularly address the knowledge gaps for new PFAS that are difficult to explore experimentally due to the lack of chemical standards.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Self-assembly</category>
  <category>Vesicles</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <category>Nanoparticles</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Yan2025_Polyfloroalkyl.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 Protein Models - A Practical Introduction to Different Structure Bias Models and their Comparison</title>
  <dc:creator>Thilo Duve, Liguo Wang, Luís Borges-Araújo, Siewert J. Marrink, Paulo C. T. Souza, and Sebastian Thallmair</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Duve2025_Martini3ProteinModels.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Duve, T., Wang, L., Borges-Araújo, L., Marrink, S. J., Souza, P. C., &amp; Thallmair, S. (2025). Martini 3 protein models - a practical introduction to different structure bias models and their comparison. bioRxiv, 2025-03.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Biophysical characterization of protein structure and dynamics is essential in many scientific fields, including molecular biology, drug discovery, and enzyme design. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations have become an increasingly important tool for studying these properties. This chapter provides a hands-on introduction to protein modeling with the Martini 3 coarse-grained (CG) force field. We outline its two-layer framework, where the first layer defines molecular topology and interactions, while the second layer applies structural bias to maintain secondary, tertiary, and quaternary structures. Three structure bias approaches - Elastic Network (EN), GōMartini, and OLIVES - are discussed, highlighting their advantages and trade-offs. Using a protein kinase as a case study, we demonstrate the step-by-step setup of Martini 3 protein models for simulations with the program package GROMACS, including system preparation, fine-tuning, and validation against atomistic reference simulations. Additionally, we explore the combination of an intrinsically disordered region (IDR) with a structured protein domain. By the end of this chapter, readers will have the necessary expertise to apply Martini 3-based protein modeling to a wide range of research applications.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Book chapter</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Protocol</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Duve2025_Martini3ProteinModels.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 building blocks for Lipid Nanoparticle design</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisbeth Ravnkilde Kjølbye, Mariana Valerio, Marketa Paloncyova, Luis Borges-Araujo, Roberto Pestana-Nobles, Fabian Grunewald, Bart MH Bruininks, Rocio Araya-Osorio, Martin Šrejber, Raul Mera-Adasme, Luca Monticelli, Siewert J Marrink, Michal Otyepka, Sangwook Wu, and Paulo CT Souza</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Kjølbye2025_Nanoparticles.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Kjølbye, L. R., Valério, M., Paloncýová, M., Borges-Araújo, L., Pestana-Nobles, R., Grünewald, F., … C.T. Souza, P. (2025). Martini 3 building blocks for Lipid Nanoparticle design. ChemRxiv. doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2024-bf4n8-v2</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) represent a promising platform for advanced drug and gene delivery, yet optimizing these particles for specific cargos and cell targets poses a complex, multifaceted challenge. Furthermore, there is a pressing need for a more comprehensive understanding of the underlying technology. Experimental studies are costly and often provide low-resolution information. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations allow us to study these particles at a higher resolution, enhancing our understanding. However, studying these systems at atomic resolutions is both challenging and computationally expensive, as well as time-consuming. Coarse-grained (CG) models, such as Martini 3, are positioned as promising tools for studying LNPs. To enable CG-MD studies of LNPs, accurate and validated models of their components are needed. Here, we present a substantial extension of the Martini 3 library of lipids, covering the most important LNP components, including over a hundred of ionizable lipid (IL) models, along with natural occurring sterol models and PEGylated lipid models. We furthermore present initial protocols for screening fusion efficacy across different lipid formulations and for constructing whole LNPs at CG resolution, enabling future studies of these nanoparticles.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Nanoparticles</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Vesicles</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Kjølbye2025_Nanoparticles.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini3-IDP: improved Martini 3 force field for disordered proteins</title>
  <dc:creator>Liguo Wang, Christopher Brasnett, Luís Borges-Araújo, Paulo C. T. Souza, and Siewert J. Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Wang2025_IDP.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wang, L., Brasnett, C., Borges-Araújo, L., Souza, P. C., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2025). Martini3-IDP: improved Martini 3 force field for disordered proteins. Nature Communications, 16(1), 1-14.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Coarse-grained (CG) molecular dynamics (MD) is widely used for the efficient simulation of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). The Martini model, one of the most popular CG force fields in biomolecular simulation, was reported to yield too compact IDP conformations, limiting its applications. Addressing this, we optimized the bonded parameters based on fitting to reference simulations of a diverse set of IDPs at atomistic resolution, resulting in a Martini3-based disordered protein model coined Martini3-IDP. This model leads to expanded IDP conformations, greatly improving the reproduction of the experimentally measured radii of gyration. Moreover, contrary to ad-hoc fixes based on scaling of protein-protein or protein-water interactions, Martini3-IDP keeps the overall interaction balance underlying Martini 3. To validate that, we perform a comprehensive testing including full-length multidomain proteins, IDP-lipid membrane binding and IDP-small molecule binding, confirming its ability to successfully capture the complex interplay between disordered proteins and diverse biomolecular components. Finally, the recently emerging concept of biomolecular condensate, through liquid-liquid phase separation, was also reproduced by Martini3-IDP for a number of both homotypic and heterotypic systems. With the improved Martini3-IDP model, we expand the ability to simulate processes involving IDPs in complex environments, at spatio-temporal scales inaccessible with all-atom models.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Coacervate</category>
  <category>Biomolecular condensates</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Wang2025_IDP.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MartiniGlass: a Tool for Enabling Visualization of Coarse-Grained Martini Topologies</title>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Brasnett, and Siewert J. Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brasnett2025_MartiniGlass.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brasnett, C., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2025). MartiniGlass: a Tool for Enabling Visualization of Coarse-Grained Martini Topologies. Journal of chemical information and modeling, 65(7), 3137-3141.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>As molecular modeling gains ever more prominence in understanding cellular processes, high quality visualization of models and dynamics has never been more important. Naturally, much molecular visualization software is written to enable the visualization of atomic level details in structures. While necessary, this means that visualization of increasingly popular coarse-grained (CG) models remains a challenge. Here, we present a Python package, MartiniGlass, that facilitates the visualization of systems simulated with the widely used CG Martini force field using the popular visualization package VMD. MartiniGlass rapidly processes molecular topologies and accounts for important topological features at CG resolution, such as secondary structure restraints, preparing them for easy visualization of simulated trajectories.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Visualization</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brasnett2025_MartiniGlass.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nanopore-Functionalized Hybrid Lipid-Block Copolymer Membranes Allow Efficient Single-Molecule Sampling and Stable Sensing of Human Serum</title>
  <dc:creator>Edo Vreeker, Fabian Grünewald, Nieck Jordy van der Heide, Andrea Bonini, Siewert J. Marrink, Katarzyna (Kasia) Tych, and Giovanni Maglia</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Vreeker2025_Nanopore.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Vreeker, E., Grünewald, F., van der Heide, N. J., Bonini, A., Marrink, S. J., Tych, K., &amp; Maglia, G. (2025). Nanopore‐Functionalized Hybrid Lipid‐Block Copolymer Membranes Allow Efficient Single‐Molecule Sampling and Stable Sensing of Human Serum. Advanced Materials, 2418462.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Biological nanopores are powerful tools for single-molecule detection, with promising potential as next-generation biosensors. A major bottleneck in nanopore analysis is the fragility of the supporting lipid membranes, that easily rupture after exposure to biological samples. Membranes comprising PMOXA-PDMS-PMOXA (poly(2-methyloxazoline-b-dimethylsiloxane-b-2-methyloxazoline)) or PBD-PEO (poly(1,2-butadiene)-b-poly(ethylene oxide)) polymers may form robust alternatives, but their suitability for the reconstitution of a broad range of nanopores has not yet been investigated. Here, PBD-PEO membranes are found to be highly robust toward applied voltages and human serum, while providing a poor environment for nanopore reconstitution. However, hybrid membranes containing a similar molar ratio of PBD11PEO8 polymers and diphytanoyl phosphatidylcholine (DPhPC) lipids show the best of both worlds: highly robust membranes suitable for the reconstitution of a wide variety of nanopores. Molecular dynamics simulations reveal that lipids form ≈12 nm domains interspersed by a polymer matrix. Nanopores partition into these lipid nanodomains and sequester lipids, possibly offering the same binding strength as in a native bilayer. Nanopores reconstituted in hybrid membranes yield efficient sampling of biomolecules and enable sensing of high concentrations of human serum. This work thus shows that hybrid membranes functionalized with nanopores allow single-molecule sensing, while forming robust interfaces, resolving an important bottleneck for novel nanopore-based biosensors.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Polymers</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Vreeker2025_Nanopore.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TS2CG as a membrane builder</title>
  <dc:creator>Fabian Schuhmann, Jan A Stevens, Neda Rahmani, Isabell Lindahl, Chelsea M Brown, Christopher Brasnett, Dimitrios Anastasiou, Adrià Bravo Vidal, Beatrice J Geiger, Siewert J Marrink, and Weria Pezeshkian</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Schuhmann2025_TS2CG.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Schuhmann, F., Stevens, J. A., Rahmani, N., Lindahl, I., Brown, C. M., Brasnett, C., … &amp; Pezeshkian, W. (2025). TS2CG as a membrane builder. bioRxiv, 2025-04.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations excel at capturing biological processes at the molecular scale but rely on a well-defined initial structure. As MD simulations now extend to whole-cell-level modeling, new tools are needed to efficiently build initial structures. Here, we introduce TS2CG version 2, designed to construct coarse-grained membrane structures with any desired shape and lateral organization. This version enables precise placement of lipids and proteins based on curvature preference, facilitating the creation of large, near-equilibrium membranes. Additional features include controlled pore generation and the placement of specific lipids at membrane edges for stabilization. Moreover, a Python interface allows users to extend functionality while maintaining the high performance of the C++ core. To demonstrate its capabilities, we showcase challenging simulations, including a Möbius strip membrane, a vesicle with lipid domain as continental plates (Martini globe), and entire mitochondrial membranes exhibiting lipid heterogeneity due to curvature, along with a comprehensive set of tutorials.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Multi-scale</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Vesicles</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Schuhmann2025_TS2CG.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Martini 3 lipidome: expanded and refined parameters improve lipid phase behavior</title>
  <dc:creator>Kasper B. Pedersen, Helgi I. Ingólfsson, Daniel P. Ramirez-Echemendia, Luís Borges-Araújo, Mikkel D. Andreasen, Charly Empereur-mot, Josef Melcr, Tugba N. Ozturk, W. F. Drew Bennett, Lisbeth R. Kjølbye, Christopher Brasnett, Valentina Corradi, Hanif M. Khan, Elio A. Cino, Jackson Crowley, Hyuntae Kim, Balázs Fábián, Ana C. Borges-Araújo, Giovanni M. Pavan, Guillaume Launay, Fabio Lolicato, Tsjerk A. Wassenaar, Manuel N. Melo, Sebastian Thallmair, Timothy S. Carpenter, Luca Monticelli, D. Peter Tieleman, Birgit Schiøtt, Paulo C. T. Souza, and Siewert J. Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Pedersen2025_Lipidome.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Pedersen, K. B., Ingólfsson, H. I., Ramirez-Echemendia, D. P., Borges-Araújo, L., Andreasen, M. D., Empereur-Mot, C., … &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2025). The Martini 3 lipidome: expanded and refined parameters improve lipid phase behavior. ACS Central Science.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Lipid membranes are central to cellular life. Complementing experiments, computational modeling has been essential in unraveling complex lipid-biomolecule interactions, crucial in both academia and industry. The Martini model, a coarse-grained force field for efficient molecular dynamics simulations, is widely used to study membrane phenomena but has faced limitations, particularly in capturing realistic lipid phase behavior. Here, we present refined Martini 3 lipid models with a mapping scheme that distinguishes lipid tails that differ by just two carbon atoms, enhancing the structural resolution and thermodynamic accuracy of model membrane systems including ternary mixtures. The expanded Martini lipid library includes thousands of models, enabling simulations of complex and biologically relevant systems. These advancements establish Martini as a robust platform for lipid-based simulations across diverse fields.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Phopholipids</category>
  <category>!🍸Core papers</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Pedersen2025_Lipidome.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bartender: Martini 3 Bonded Terms via Quantum Mechanics-based Molecular Dynamics</title>
  <dc:creator>Gilberto P Pereira, Riccardo Alessandri, Moisés Domínguez, Rocío Araya-Osorio, Linus Grünewald, Luís Borges-Araújo, Sangwook Wu, Siewert J Marrink, Paulo Cesar Telles de Souza, and Raul Mera-Adasme</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Pereira2024_Bartender.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Pereira, G. P., Alessandri, R., Domínguez, M., Araya-Osorio, R., Grünewald, L., Borges-Araújo, L., … &amp; Mera-Adasme, R. (2024). Bartender: Martini 3 Bonded Terms via Quantum Mechanics-based Molecular Dynamics.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Coarse-grained (CG) molecular dynamics (MD) simulations have grown in applicability over the years. The recently released version of the Martini CG force field (Martini 3) has been successfully applied to simulate many processes, including protein-ligand binding. However, the current ligand parameterization scheme is manual and requires an a priori reference all-atom (AA) simulation for benchmarking. For systems with suboptimal AA parameters, which are often unknown, this translates into a CG model which does not reproduce the true dynamical behavior of the underlying molecule. Here we present Bartender, a quantum mechanics (QM)/MD-based parameterization tool written in Go. Bartender harnesses the power of QM simulations and produces reasonable bonded terms for Martini 3 CG models of small molecules in an efficient and user-friendly manner. For small, ring-like molecules, Bartender generates models whose properties are indistinguishable from the human-made models. For more complex, drug-like ligands, it is able to fit functional forms beyond simple harmonic dihedrals, and thus better captures their dynamical behavior. Bartender has the power to both increase the efficiency and the accuracy of Martini 3-based high-throughput applications by producing stable and physically realistic CG models.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Multi-scale</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Pereira2024_Bartender.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Benchmarking coarse-grained simulation methods for investigation of transport tunnels in enzymes</title>
  <dc:creator>Nishita Mandal, Jan A. Stevens, Adolfo B. Poma, Bartlomiej Surpeta, Carlos Sequeiros-Borja, Aravind Selvaram Thirunavukarasu, Siewert-Jan Marrink, and Jan Brezovsky.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Mandal2024_TunnelEnzyme.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Mandal, N., Stevens, J. A., Poma, A. B., Surpeta, B., Sequeiros-Borja, C., Thirunavukarasu, A. S., … &amp; Brezovsky, J. (2024). Benchmarking coarse-grained simulation methods for investigation of transport tunnels in enzymes. bioRxiv, 2024-09.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Enzymes are pivotal to numerous biological processes, often featuring buried active sites linked to the surrounding solvent through intricate and dynamic tunnels. These tunnels are vital for facilitating substrate access, enabling product release, and regulating solvent exchange, which collectively influence enzymatic function and efficiency. Consequently, knowledge of tunnels is key for a holistic understanding of the effect of mutations as well as predicting drug residence times. Unfortunately, most transport tunnels are transient, i.e., equipped by molecular gates, rendering their opening a rare event that is often notoriously hard to study with conventional molecular dynamics simulations. To overcome the sampling limitation of such simulations, this study investigated the efficacy of three different coarse-grained (CG) molecular dynamics simulation methods for inferring enzyme tunnel structure and dynamics. Here, we covered the Martini and SIRAH models with different restraint protocols providing stability to CG proteins while to some extent biasing the sampling towards a reference structure. By contrasting CG results with all-atom simulations, we benchmarked the ability of CG methods to replicate ensemble characteristics of complex tunnel networks in haloalkane dehalogenase LinB and two of its mutants with engineered tunnel networks. The assessed tunnel parameters are essential for prioritizing functionally relevant tunnels and delineating the effect of mutations on transport tunnels. Our findings reveal that while CG methods significantly enhance the efficiency of tunnel analyses, some of them, like Martini with Elastic network restraints, were limited in recapitulating all-atom tunnel dynamics due to the structural bias applied. In contrast, the Martini Gō model even captured the intricate details of mutation perturbing tunnel dynamics. All studied CG methods performed well in capturing the geometry of tunnel ensembles in line with all-atom simulations. Additionally, the wider applicability of CG methods was verified by analyzing tunnel networks of nine enzymes from different combinations of structural and functional classes, demonstrating their potential to uncover new tunnel phenomena and validate their utility in broader biological and functional contexts. This comprehensive evaluation underscores the strengths and constraints of CG simulations in capturing enzyme tunnels and benefiting from their computational speed for studying huge datasets of enzymes. These insights are valuable for enzyme engineering, drug design, and understanding enzyme function while benefitting from the efficiency of coarse-grained models.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Multi-scale</category>
  <category>Drug design</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Mandal2024_TunnelEnzyme.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building complex membranes with Martini 3</title>
  <dc:creator>Tugba Nur Ozturk, Melanie König, Timothy S Carpenter, Kasper B Pedersen, Tsjerk A Wassenaar, Helgi I Ingólfsson, and Siewert J Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Ozturk2024_ComplexMembranes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Ozturk, T. N., König, M., Carpenter, T. S., Pedersen, K. B., Wassenaar, T. A., Ingólfsson, H. I., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2024). Building complex membranes with Martini 3. Methods in Enzymology.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The Martini model is a popular force field for coarse-grained simulations. Membranes have always been at the center of its development, with the latest version, Martini 3, showing great promise in capturing more and more realistic behavior. In this chapter we provide a step-by-step tutorial on how to construct starting configurations, run initial simulations and perform dedicated analysis for membrane-based systems of increasing complexity, including leaflet asymmetry, curvature gradients and embedding of membrane proteins.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Book chapter</category>
  <category>Protocol</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Ozturk2024_ComplexMembranes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Capturing chemical reactions inside biomolecular condensates with reactive Martini simulations</title>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Brasnett, Armin Kiani, Selim Sami, Sijbren Otto &amp; Siewert J. Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Brasnett2024_ReactionCondensates.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brasnett, C., Kiani, A., Sami, S. &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2024). Capturing chemical reactions inside biomolecular condensates with reactive Martini simulations. Commun Chem 7, 151.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Biomolecular condensates are phase separated systems that play an important role in the spatio-temporal organisation of cells. Their distinct physico-chemical nature offers a unique environment for chemical reactions to occur. The compartmentalisation of chemical reactions is also believed to be central to the development of early life. To demonstrate how molecular dynamics may be used to capture chemical reactions in condensates, here we perform reactive molecular dynamics simulations using the coarse-grained Martini forcefield. We focus on the formation of rings of benzene-1,3-dithiol inside a synthetic peptide-based condensate, and find that the ring size distribution shifts to larger macrocycles compared to when the reaction takes place in an aqueous environment. Moreover, reaction rates are noticeably increased when the peptides simultaneously undergo phase separation, hinting that condensates may act as chaperones in recruiting molecules to reaction hubs.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Biomolecular condensates</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <category>Reactive</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Brasnett2024_ReactionCondensates.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring the Ligand Binding and Conformational Dynamics of the Substrate-Binding Domain 1 of the ABC Transporter GlnPQ</title>
  <dc:creator>Mariia Nemchinova, Gea K. Schuurman-Wolters, Jacob J. Whittaker, Valentina Arkhipova, Siewert J. Marrink, Bert Poolman, and Albert Guskov</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Nemchinova2024_GlnPQ.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Nemchinova, M., Schuurman-Wolters, G. K., Whittaker, J. J., Arkhipova, V., Marrink, S. J., Poolman, B., &amp; Guskov, A. (2024). Exploring the Ligand Binding and Conformational Dynamics of the Substrate-Binding Domain 1 of the ABC Transporter GlnPQ. The Journal of Physical Chemistry B, 128(32), 7822-7832.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The adenosine triphosphate (ATP)-binding cassette (ABC) importer GlnPQ from Lactococcus lactis has two sequential covalently linked substrate-binding domains (SBDs), which capture the substrates and deliver them to the translocon. The two SBDs differ in their ligand specificities, binding affinities and the distance to the transmembrane domain; interestingly, both SBDs can bind their ligands simultaneously without affecting each other. In this work, we studied the binding of ligands to both SBDs using X-ray crystallography and molecular dynamics simulations. We report three high-resolution structures of SBD1, namely, the wild-type SBD1 with bound asparagine or arginine, and E184D SBD1 with glutamine bound. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations provide a detailed insight into the dynamics associated with open-closed transitions of the SBDs.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <category>Metabolites</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Nemchinova2024_GlnPQ.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hybrid lipid-block copolymer membranes enable stable reconstitution of a wide range of nanopores and robust sampling of serum</title>
  <dc:creator>Edo Vreeker, Fabian Grunewald, Nieck van der Heide, Siewert-Jan Marrink, Katarzyna Tych, and Giovanni Maglia</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Vreeker2024_Nanopores.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Vreeker, E., Grunewald, F., van der Heide, N., Marrink, S. J., Tych, K., &amp; Maglia, G. (2024). Hybrid lipid-block copolymer membranes enable stable reconstitution of a wide range of nanopores and robust sampling of serum. bioRxiv, 2024-05.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Biological nanopores are powerful tools for detecting biomolecules at the single-molecule level, making them appealing as sensors for biological samples. However, the lipid membranes in which nanopores reside can be unstable in the presence of biological fluids. Here, membranes formed with the amphiphilic polymers PMOXA-PDMS-PMOXA and PBD-PEO are tested as potential alternatives for nanopore sensing. We demonstrate that polymer membranes can possess increased stability towards applied potentials and high concentrations of human serum, but that the stable insertion of a wide range of biological nanopores is most often compromised. Alternatively, hybrid polymer-lipid membranes comprising a 1:1 w/w mixture of PBD11PEO8 and DPhPC showed high electrical and biochemical stability while creating a suitable environment for all tested nanopores. Analytes such as proteins, DNA and sugars were efficiently sampled, indicating that in hybrid membranes nanopores showed native-like properties. Molecular dynamics simulations revealed that lipids form ∼12 nm domains interspersed by a polymer matrix. Nanopores partitioned into these lipid nanodomains and sequestered lipids possibly offering the same binding strength as in a native bilayer. This work shows that single-molecule analysis with nanopores in [PBD11PEO8 + DPhPC] membranes is feasible and present stable recordings in the presence of human serum. These results pave the way towards novel nanopore-based biosensors.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Polymers</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Vreeker2024_Nanopores.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 Coarse-Grained Model for the Cofactors Involved in Photosynthesis</title>
  <dc:creator>Maria Gabriella Chiariello, Rubi Zarmiento-Garcia and Siewert-Jan Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Chiariello2024_CofactorsPhotosynthesis.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Chiariello, M. G., Zarmiento-Garcia, R., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2024). Martini 3 Coarse-Grained Model for the Cofactors Involved in Photosynthesis. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 25(14), 7947.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>As a critical step in advancing the simulation of photosynthetic complexes, we present the Martini 3 coarse-grained (CG) models of key cofactors associated with light harvesting (LHCII) proteins and the photosystem II (PSII) core complex. Our work focuses on the parametrization of beta-carotene, plastoquinone/quinol, violaxanthin, lutein, neoxanthin, chlorophyll A, chlorophyll B, and heme. We derived the CG parameters to match the all-atom reference simulations, while structural and thermodynamic properties of the cofactors were compared to experimental values when available. To further assess the reliability of the parameterization, we tested the behavior of these cofactors within their physiological environments, specifically in a lipid bilayer and bound to photosynthetic complexes. The results demonstrate that our CG models maintain the essential features required for realistic simulations. This work lays the groundwork for detailed simulations of the PSII-LHCII super-complex, providing a robust parameter set for future studies.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Metabolites</category>
  <category>Cofactors</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Chiariello2024_CofactorsPhotosynthesis.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 OliGo̅mers: A Scalable Approach for Multimers and Fibrils in GROMACS</title>
  <dc:creator>Ksenia Korshunova, Julius Kiuru, Juho Liekkinen, Giray Enkavi, Ilpo Vattulainen and Bart M. H. Bruininks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Korshunova2024_OliGomers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Korshunova, K., Kiuru, J., Liekkinen, J., Enkavi, G., Vattulainen, I., &amp; Bruininks, B. M. (2024). Martini 3 OliGo̅mers: A Scalable Approach for Multimers and Fibrils in GROMACS. Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Martini 3 is a widely used coarse-grained simulation method for large-scale biomolecular simulations. It can be combined with a Go̅ model to realistically describe higher-order protein structures while allowing the folding and unfolding events. However, as of today, this method has largely been used only for individual monomers. In this article, we describe how the Go̅ model can be implemented within the framework of Martini 3 for a multimer system, taking into account both intramolecular and intermolecular interactions in an oligomeric protein system. We demonstrate the method by showing how it can be applied to both structural stability maintenance and assembly/disassembly of protein oligomers, using aquaporin tetramer, insulin dimer, and amyloid-β fibril as examples. We find that addition of intermolecular Go̅ potentials stabilizes the quaternary structure of proteins. The strength of the Go̅ potentials can be tuned so that the internal fluctuations of proteins match the behavior of atomistic simulation models, however, the results also show that the use of too strong intermolecular Go̅ potentials weakens the chemical specificity of oligomerization. The Martini-Go̅ model presented here enables the use of Go̅ potentials in oligomeric molecular systems in a computationally efficient and parallelizable manner, especially in the case of homopolymers, where the number of identical protein monomers is high. This paves the way for coarse-grained simulations of large protein complexes, such as viral protein capsids and prion fibrils, in complex biological environments.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Forcefield</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Self-assembly</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2024/Korshunova2024_OliGomers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
