<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Martini Force Field Initiative</title>
<link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/</link>
<atom:link href="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://cgmartini.nl/images/martini.gif</url>
<title>Martini Force Field Initiative</title>
<link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.8.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A Comparative Nanomechanical Study of Antibody and Nanobody Binding to SARS-CoV-2 Variants</title>
  <dc:creator>Luis F Cofas-Vargas, Gustavo E Olivos-Ramirez, Siewert-Jan Marrink, and Adolfo B Poma</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/CofasVargas2025_AntibodyBinding.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Cofas-Vargas, L. F., Olivos-Ramirez, G. E., Marrink, S. J., &amp; Poma, A. B. (2025). A Comparative Nanomechanical Study of Antibody and Nanobody Binding to SARS-CoV-2 Variants. bioRxiv, 2025-09.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The receptor-binding domain of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein is the principal target of neutralizing antibodies (Abs) and nanobodies (Nbs). Although their thermodynamic binding properties have been extensively characterized, their stability under mechanical force remains less understood. Here, we perform a comparative nanomechanical analysis of three Abs (PDI-231, S2X259, and R1-32) and three Nbs (R14, C1, and n3113.1) bound to the RBD from the WT strain and the Omicron BA.4 and JN.1 variants. Using coarse-grained steered molecular dynamics within the GōMartini 3 framework, we identified distinct force–response behaviors shaped by epitope topology, binding architecture, and variant-specific mutations. Ab/RBD dissociation was characterized by asymmetric rupture events, variant-dependent unfolding of RBD segments, and occasional deformation of antibody constant domains. Analysis of single-chain systems revealed that the heavy chain acts as the main load-bearing element, while the light chain sustains a consistent but weaker mechanical response. For the two-chain Ab system, the cooperative action of both chains enhances stability, enabling complexes to withstand rupture forces in the range of 500 pN. By contrast, Nb/RBD complexes dissociated primarily through rigid-body mechanisms, transmitting force more directly to the RBD interface with minimal structural disruption. Together, these results demonstrate that mechanical resilience emerges from immune complex topology and inter-chain cooperation, providing complementary insights beyond affinity into the design of therapeutics resilient to viral evolution.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Enhanced sampling</category>
  <category>Drug design</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/CofasVargas2025_AntibodyBinding.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A systematic approach to parameterization of disaccharides for the Martini 3 coarse-grained force-field</title>
  <dc:creator>Astrid F Brandner, Iain PS Smith, Siewert J Marrink, Paulo CT Souza, and Syma Khalid</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brandner2025_Disaccharides.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brandner, A. F., Smith, I. P., Marrink, S. J., Souza, P. C., &amp; Khalid, S. (2025). Systematic Approach to Parametrization of Disaccharides for the Martini 3 Coarse-Grained Force Field. Journal of chemical information and modeling.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Sugars are ubiquitous in biology; they occur in all kingdoms of life. Despite their prevalence, they have often been somewhat neglected in studies of structure–dynamics–function relationships of macromolecules to which they are attached, with the exception of nucleic acids. This is largely due to the inherent difficulties of not only studying the conformational dynamics of sugars using experimental methods but indeed also resolving their static structures. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations offer a route to the prediction of conformational ensembles and the time-dependent behavior of sugars and glycosylated macromolecules. However, at the all-atom level of detail, MD simulations are often too computationally demanding to allow a systematic investigation of molecular interactions in systems of interest. To overcome this, large scale simulations of complex biological systems have profited from advances in coarse-grained (CG) simulations. Perhaps the most widely used CG force field for biomolecular simulations is Martini. Here, we present a parameter set for glucose- and mannose-based disaccharides for Martini 3. The generation of the CG parameters from atomistic trajectories is automated as fully as possible, and where not possible, we provide details of the protocol used for manual intervention.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Glycans</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brandner2025_Disaccharides.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Allosteric pathway connects Zn (II) loss from SOD1 to known pathogenic mechanisms</title>
  <dc:creator>Rocío Araya-Osorio, Moisés Dominguez, Sebastian Thallmair, Siewert J Marrink, Paulo CT Souza, and Raúl Mera-Adasme</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/ArayaOsorio2025_SOD1.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Araya-Osorio, R., Dominguez, M., Thallmair, S., Marrink, S. J., Souza, P. C., &amp; Mera-Adasme, R. (2025). Allosteric pathway connects Zn (II) loss from SOD1 to known pathogenic mechanisms. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 148349.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Cu,Zn superoxide dismutase (SOD1) is one of the proteins with mutations linked to hereditary forms of the amyotrophic lateral sclerosis neurodegenerative disorder. The protein is known for its enzymatic activity, but it has been shown to also have regulatory functions, which could be related to its pathogenic potential. Seemingly unrelated to its regulatory roles, the most important hypothesis on SOD1 pathogenicity is related to misfolding of the protein, specifically centered on the region corresponding to its residues 28–38. The present work explores the structural and dynamical effect of Zn(II) removal from SOD1, which is known to influence its regulatory roles, with coarse-grained simulations of 450 µs per system. In agreement with experiment, we see an increased solvent exposure of the regulatory region (residues 5–18). We also see an increased solvent exposure of the misfolding-critical 28–38 region. We unveil the mechanism and interactions connecting Zn(II) loss, and solvent exposure of both regions. The present work allows for an unified understanding of two different pathogenic mechanisms of SOD1.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/ArayaOsorio2025_SOD1.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An integrative modelling approach to the mitochondrial cristae</title>
  <dc:creator>Chelsea M. Brown, Marieke S. S. Westendorp, Rubi Zarmiento-Garcia, Jan A. Stevens, Bart M. H. Bruininks, Sarah L. Rouse, Siewert J. Marrink &amp; Tsjerk A. Wassenaar </dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brown2025_Cristae.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brown, C. M., Westendorp, M. S., Zarmiento-Garcia, R., Stevens, J. A., Bruininks, B. M., Rouse, S. L., Marrink, S.J. &amp; Wassenaar, T. A. (2025). An integrative modelling approach to the mitochondrial cristae. Communications Biology, 8(1), 972.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Mitochondria are implicated in many cellular functions such as energy production and apoptosis but also disease pathogenesis. To effectively perform these roles, the mitochondrial inner membrane has invaginations known as cristae that dramatically increase the surface area. This works to provide more space for membrane proteins that are essential to the roles of mitochondria. While separate components of this have been studied computationally, it remains a challenge to combine elements into an overall model. Here, we present a comprehensive model of a crista junction from a human mitochondrion and the accompanying workflow to construct it. Our coarse-grained representation of a crista shows how various experimentally determined features of organelles can be combined with molecular modelling to give insights into the interactions and dynamics of complicated biological systems. This work is presented as an initial ‘living’ model for this system, intended to be built upon and improved as our understanding, methodology and resources develop.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brown2025_Cristae.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An optimized contact map for GōMartini 3 enabling conformational changes in protein assemblies</title>
  <dc:creator>Gustavo Enrique Ramirez-Olivos, Luis Fernando Cofas-Vargas, Siewert-Jan Marrink, and Adolfo Poma</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/RamirezOlivos2025_GoContactMap.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Ramirez-Olivos, G. E., Cofas-Vargas, L. F., Marrink, S. J., &amp; Poma, A. (2025). An optimized contact map for GōMartini 3 enabling conformational changes in protein assemblies. bioRxiv, 2025-11.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Advances in structural biology, particularly cryo-electron microscopy, have enabled high-resolution characterization of complex biomolecular assemblies. These developments emphasize the need for computational approaches capable of describing biologically relevant conformational changes over extended timescales. GōMartini 3 is a coarse-grained approach that demonstrates computational efficiency and versatility across several systems, from protein-binding membranes and soluble proteins to intrinsically disordered proteins, while preserving key physicochemical features. In this work, we introduce an optimized approach that integrates dynamic contact information from AA-MD simulations to refine the contact map in GōMartini simulations. Specifically, we define high-frequency contacts (HFC), which reduce the number of original Gō contacts set by ≈20–30%, thereby improving the representation of conformational states beyond the original approach. Benchmarking different contact-selection criteria revealed that including intra- and interchain HFC captures structural flexibility and domain dynamics. The method was tested on three small soluble proteins and on the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. Overall, the optimized contact map improves sampling efficiency and expands the accessible conformational landscape relative to the original GōMartini 3 implementation. The full framework is available as an open-source resource for large-scale simulations of biomolecular assemblies.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Forcefield</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/RamirezOlivos2025_GoContactMap.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Efficient Protein-Ligand Binding Free Energy Estimation with Coarse-Grained Funnel Metadynamics</title>
  <dc:creator>Andrea Grazzi, Chelsea M Brown, Maurizio Sironi, Siewert J Marrink, and Stefano Pieraccini</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Grazzi2025_LigandBindingEnergy.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Grazzi, A., Brown, C. M., Sironi, M., Marrink, S. J., &amp; Pieraccini, S. (2025). Efficient Protein-Ligand Binding Free Energy Estimation with Coarse-Grained Funnel Metadynamics.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Despite considerable advances in computational chemistry, bridging the gap between the accuracy of all-atom molecular dynamics (AA-MD) and the high-throughput capabilities of docking remains an unsolved problem in protein-ligand binding free energy predictions. In this work, we propose to address this challenge through coarse-grained funnel metadynamics (CG-FMD) with the Martini 3 forcefield. This approach combines the reduced computational cost of a CG representation with state-of-the-art enhanced sampling techniques and the interpretability of a physics-based forcefield. Specifically, the binding of colchicine to two different protein targets was modeled at both AA and CG resolutions, and the corresponding ΔGbind predictions were compared with experimental references. Additionally, the robustness of CG-FMD-based ΔGbind predictions was evaluated with respect to various aspects of the simulation setup by collecting more than 7 milliseconds of CG-FMD simulations. The results demonstrate that CGFMD yields ΔGbind estimates comparable to experimental values while requiring only a fraction of the computational cost of AA-MD simulations. Moreover, the extensive sampling achievable with CG-FMD reduces statistical uncertainty in the final predictions, effectively compensating for the simplified system representation. Future work should build upon these methodological insights to broaden the scope of ligands and targets explored.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Enhanced sampling</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <category>Multi-scale</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Grazzi2025_LigandBindingEnergy.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gradient-Based Optimization of Force Field Parameters for Martini Lipid Models</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel P. Ramirez-Echemendia, Ryan K. Krueger, D. Peter Tieleman, Megan C. Engel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Ramirez-Echemendia2025_JaxMartini.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Ramirez-Echemendia, D. P., Krueger, R. K., Tieleman, D. P., &amp; Engel, M. C. (2025). Gradient-Based Optimization of Force Field Parameters for Martini Lipid Models. Chemistry. https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-dtt4k</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Physics-based coarse-grained (CG) models are widely used in (bio)molecular simulations, yet their parameterization remains challenging and labor-intensive. In this work, we demonstrate how recently developed gradient-based optimization methods can substantially accelerate the refinement of CG force field (FF) parameters within the Martini framework, a cornerstone of modern CG modeling. Using Martini lipid models as a testbed, we explore three increasingly challenging optimization problems. First, a single phosphatidylcholine (PC) lipid, where we optimize bonded parameters by fitting simultaneously to top-down membrane observables (area per lipid, bilayer thickness, and transition temperature) and bottom-up atomistic bond and angle distributions. We then scale the workflow to eight different PC lipids, demonstrating robust performance in a complex multi-system landscape and an order-of-magnitude reduction in computational cost relative to population-based heuristic schemes. Finally, to evaluate performance in higher-dimensional parameter spaces, we additionally optimize the non-bonded parameters of the solvent-free Dry Martini FF, demonstrating that the method scales effectively with increasing numbers of adjustable parameters. Collectively, these results suggest that the large, expert-coordinated workflows that have historically characterized the parameterization of community-driven CG models like Martini can be efficiently streamlined by fully automated, objective-driven gradient-based optimizations.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Phospholipids</category>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Ramirez-Echemendia2025_JaxMartini.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GōMartini 3: From large conformational changes in proteins to environmental bias corrections</title>
  <dc:creator>Paulo CT Souza, Luis P Borges Araujo, Chris Brasnett, Rodrigo A Moreira, Fabian Grunewald, Peter Park, Liguo Wang, Hafez Razmazma, Ana C Borges-Araujo, Luis F Cofas-Vargas, Luca Monticelli, Raul Mera-Adasme, Manuel N Melo, Sangwook Wu, Siewert J Marrink, Adolfo B Poma, and Sebastian Thallmair</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Souza2025_GoMartini.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Souza, P. C., Borges-Araújo, L., Brasnett, C., Moreira, R. A., Grünewald, F., Park, P., … &amp; Thallmair, S. (2025). GōMartini 3: from large conformational changes in proteins to environmental bias corrections. Nature Communications, 16(1), 4051.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Coarse-grained modeling has become an important tool to supplement experimental measurements, allowing access to spatio-temporal scales beyond all-atom based approaches. The GōMartini model combines structure- and physics-based coarse-grained approaches, balancing computational efficiency and accurate representation of protein dynamics with the capabilities of studying proteins in different biological environments. This paper introduces an enhanced GōMartini model, which combines a virtual-site implementation of Gō models with Martini 3. The implementation has been extensively tested by the community since the release of the reparametrized version of Martini. This work demonstrates the capabilities of the model in diverse case studies, ranging from protein-membrane binding to protein-ligand interactions and AFM force profile calculations. The model is also versatile, as it can address recent inaccuracies reported in the Martini protein model. Lastly, the paper discusses the advantages, limitations, and future perspectives of the Martini 3 protein model and its combination with Gō models.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Forcefield</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Souza2025_GoMartini.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hexokinase-I directly binds to a charged membrane-buried glutamate of mitochondrial VDAC1 and VDAC2</title>
  <dc:creator>Sebastian Bieker, Michael Timme, Nils Woge, Dina G Hassan, Chelsea M Brown, Siewert J Marrink, Manuel N Melo, and Joost CM Holthuis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Bieker2025_Hexokinase1VDAC.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Bieker, S., Timme, M., Woge, N., Hassan, D. G., Brown, C. M., Marrink, S. J., … &amp; Holthuis, J. C. (2025). Hexokinase-I directly binds to a charged membrane-buried glutamate of mitochondrial VDAC1 and VDAC2. Communications biology, 8(1), 212.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Binding of hexokinase HKI to mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion channels (VDACs) has far-reaching physiological implications. However, the structural basis of this interaction is unclear. Combining computer simulations with experiments in cells, we here show that complex assembly relies on intimate contacts between the N-terminal α-helix of HKI and a charged membrane-buried glutamate on the outer wall of VDAC1 and VDAC2. Protonation of this residue blocks complex formation in silico while acidification of the cytosol causes a reversable release of HKI from mitochondria. Membrane insertion of HKI occurs adjacent to the bilayer-facing glutamate where a pair of polar channel residues mediates a marked thinning of the cytosolic leaflet. Disrupting the membrane thinning capacity of VDAC1 dramatically impairs its ability to bind HKI in silico and in cells. Our data reveal key topological and mechanistic insights into HKI-VDAC complex assembly that may benefit the development of therapeutics to counter pathogenic imbalances in this process.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>pH</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Bieker2025_Hexokinase1VDAC.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Insight into the Self-Assembly Behaviors of Per-and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances Using a Computational Microscope</title>
  <dc:creator>Bei Yan, Riccardo Alessandri, Siewert J Marrink, Linda S Lee, and Jinxia Liu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Yan2025_Polyfloroalkyl.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Yan, B., Alessandri, R., Marrink, S. J., Lee, L. S., &amp; Liu, J. (2025). Insight into the Self-Assembly Behaviors of Per-and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances Using a “Computational Microscope”. Environmental Science &amp; Technology Letters, 12(5), 626-631.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Aqueous film-forming foams (AFFFs) have been extensively used for firefighting, contributing to environmental contamination with per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). Most PFAS in AFFFs are fluorosurfactants, known to self-assemble into large supramolecular assemblies in the field of physical chemistry; however, the application of this phenomenon to understanding environmental fate has not been studied. We hypothesize that self-assembled PFAS likely enhance the long-term retention of PFAS in subsurface environments, acting as a continuous source of dissolved PFAS. Thus, characterizing these self-assemblies and understanding their aggregation dynamics are crucial for assessing the fate and transport of PFAS. Despite the utility of molecular dynamics (MD) simulation in studying surfactant behaviors, fluorosurfactants have been underexplored due to the lack of force field parameters. In this study, we developed coarse-grained (CG) force field parameters for fluorosurfactants based on the Martini 3 model and performed CG-MD simulations. These “computational microscope” simulations reveal the self-assembly behavior of selected PFAS, aligning with experimental cryo-transmission electron microscopy observations and providing mechanistic insights. Our work sheds light on the evolution of solvated PFAS self-assemblies over time and space. The CG-MD simulation can particularly address the knowledge gaps for new PFAS that are difficult to explore experimentally due to the lack of chemical standards.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Self-assembly</category>
  <category>Vesicles</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <category>Nanoparticles</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Yan2025_Polyfloroalkyl.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 Protein Models - A Practical Introduction to Different Structure Bias Models and their Comparison</title>
  <dc:creator>Thilo Duve, Liguo Wang, Luís Borges-Araújo, Siewert J. Marrink, Paulo C. T. Souza, and Sebastian Thallmair</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Duve2025_Martini3ProteinModels.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Duve, T., Wang, L., Borges-Araújo, L., Marrink, S. J., Souza, P. C., &amp; Thallmair, S. (2025). Martini 3 protein models - a practical introduction to different structure bias models and their comparison. bioRxiv, 2025-03.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Biophysical characterization of protein structure and dynamics is essential in many scientific fields, including molecular biology, drug discovery, and enzyme design. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations have become an increasingly important tool for studying these properties. This chapter provides a hands-on introduction to protein modeling with the Martini 3 coarse-grained (CG) force field. We outline its two-layer framework, where the first layer defines molecular topology and interactions, while the second layer applies structural bias to maintain secondary, tertiary, and quaternary structures. Three structure bias approaches - Elastic Network (EN), GōMartini, and OLIVES - are discussed, highlighting their advantages and trade-offs. Using a protein kinase as a case study, we demonstrate the step-by-step setup of Martini 3 protein models for simulations with the program package GROMACS, including system preparation, fine-tuning, and validation against atomistic reference simulations. Additionally, we explore the combination of an intrinsically disordered region (IDR) with a structured protein domain. By the end of this chapter, readers will have the necessary expertise to apply Martini 3-based protein modeling to a wide range of research applications.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Book chapter</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Protocol</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Duve2025_Martini3ProteinModels.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 building blocks for Lipid Nanoparticle design</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisbeth Ravnkilde Kjølbye, Mariana Valerio, Marketa Paloncyova, Luis Borges-Araujo, Roberto Pestana-Nobles, Fabian Grunewald, Bart MH Bruininks, Rocio Araya-Osorio, Martin Šrejber, Raul Mera-Adasme, Luca Monticelli, Siewert J Marrink, Michal Otyepka, Sangwook Wu, and Paulo CT Souza</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Kjølbye2025_Nanoparticles.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Kjølbye, L. R., Valério, M., Paloncýová, M., Borges-Araújo, L., Pestana-Nobles, R., Grünewald, F., … C.T. Souza, P. (2025). Martini 3 building blocks for Lipid Nanoparticle design. ChemRxiv. doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2024-bf4n8-v2</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) represent a promising platform for advanced drug and gene delivery, yet optimizing these particles for specific cargos and cell targets poses a complex, multifaceted challenge. Furthermore, there is a pressing need for a more comprehensive understanding of the underlying technology. Experimental studies are costly and often provide low-resolution information. Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations allow us to study these particles at a higher resolution, enhancing our understanding. However, studying these systems at atomic resolutions is both challenging and computationally expensive, as well as time-consuming. Coarse-grained (CG) models, such as Martini 3, are positioned as promising tools for studying LNPs. To enable CG-MD studies of LNPs, accurate and validated models of their components are needed. Here, we present a substantial extension of the Martini 3 library of lipids, covering the most important LNP components, including over a hundred of ionizable lipid (IL) models, along with natural occurring sterol models and PEGylated lipid models. We furthermore present initial protocols for screening fusion efficacy across different lipid formulations and for constructing whole LNPs at CG resolution, enabling future studies of these nanoparticles.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Nanoparticles</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Vesicles</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Kjølbye2025_Nanoparticles.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 coarse-grained models for carbon nanomaterials</title>
  <dc:creator>Roshan Shrestha, Riccardo Alessandri, Martin Vögele, Paulo CT Souza, Siewert-Jan Marrink, and Luca Monticelli</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Shrestha2025_Nanomaterials.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Shrestha, R., Alessandri, R., Vögele, M., Hilpert, C., Souza, P. C., Marrink, S. J., &amp; Monticelli, L. (2025). Martini 3 coarse-grained models for carbon nanomaterials. Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation, 21(18), 9035-9053.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The Martini model is a coarse-grained force field allowing simulations of biomolecular systems as well as a range of materials including different types of nanomaterials of technological interest. Recently, a new version of the force field (version 3) has been released that includes new parameters for lipids, proteins, carbohydrates, and a number of small molecules, but not yet carbon nanomaterials. Here, we present new Martini models for three major types of carbon nanomaterials: fullerene, carbon nanotubes, and graphene. The new models were parametrized within the Martini 3 framework, and reproduce semiquantitatively a range of properties for each material. In particular, the model of fullerene yields excellent solid-state properties and good properties in solution, including correct trends in partitioning between different solvents and realistic translocation across lipid membranes. The models of carbon nanotubes reproduce the atomistic behavior of nanotube porins spanning lipid bilayers. The model of graphene reproduces structural and elastic properties, as well as trends in experimental adsorption enthalpies of organic molecules. All new models can be used in large-scale simulations to study the interaction with the wide variety of molecules already available in the Martini 3 force field, including biomolecular and synthetic systems.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Nanoparticles</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Materials science</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Shrestha2025_Nanomaterials.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini3-IDP: improved Martini 3 force field for disordered proteins</title>
  <dc:creator>Liguo Wang, Christopher Brasnett, Luís Borges-Araújo, Paulo C. T. Souza, and Siewert J. Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Wang2025_IDP.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wang, L., Brasnett, C., Borges-Araújo, L., Souza, P. C., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2025). Martini3-IDP: improved Martini 3 force field for disordered proteins. Nature Communications, 16(1), 1-14.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Coarse-grained (CG) molecular dynamics (MD) is widely used for the efficient simulation of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). The Martini model, one of the most popular CG force fields in biomolecular simulation, was reported to yield too compact IDP conformations, limiting its applications. Addressing this, we optimized the bonded parameters based on fitting to reference simulations of a diverse set of IDPs at atomistic resolution, resulting in a Martini3-based disordered protein model coined Martini3-IDP. This model leads to expanded IDP conformations, greatly improving the reproduction of the experimentally measured radii of gyration. Moreover, contrary to ad-hoc fixes based on scaling of protein-protein or protein-water interactions, Martini3-IDP keeps the overall interaction balance underlying Martini 3. To validate that, we perform a comprehensive testing including full-length multidomain proteins, IDP-lipid membrane binding and IDP-small molecule binding, confirming its ability to successfully capture the complex interplay between disordered proteins and diverse biomolecular components. Finally, the recently emerging concept of biomolecular condensate, through liquid-liquid phase separation, was also reproduced by Martini3-IDP for a number of both homotypic and heterotypic systems. With the improved Martini3-IDP model, we expand the ability to simulate processes involving IDPs in complex environments, at spatio-temporal scales inaccessible with all-atom models.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Parametrization</category>
  <category>Coacervate</category>
  <category>Biomolecular condensates</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Wang2025_IDP.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MartiniGlass: a Tool for Enabling Visualization of Coarse-Grained Martini Topologies</title>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Brasnett, and Siewert J. Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brasnett2025_MartiniGlass.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Brasnett, C., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2025). MartiniGlass: a Tool for Enabling Visualization of Coarse-Grained Martini Topologies. Journal of chemical information and modeling, 65(7), 3137-3141.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>As molecular modeling gains ever more prominence in understanding cellular processes, high quality visualization of models and dynamics has never been more important. Naturally, much molecular visualization software is written to enable the visualization of atomic level details in structures. While necessary, this means that visualization of increasingly popular coarse-grained (CG) models remains a challenge. Here, we present a Python package, MartiniGlass, that facilitates the visualization of systems simulated with the widely used CG Martini force field using the popular visualization package VMD. MartiniGlass rapidly processes molecular topologies and accounts for important topological features at CG resolution, such as secondary structure restraints, preparing them for easy visualization of simulated trajectories.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Visualization</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Brasnett2025_MartiniGlass.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Fatty Acid Extraction Using a Type V Deep Eutectic Solvent with Tunable Hydrophobicity</title>
  <dc:creator>Petteri A Vainikka, Matthijs J Tadema, and Siewert J Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Vainikka2025_FattyAcidExtraction.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Vainikka, P. A., Tadema, M. J., &amp; Marrink, S. J. (2025). Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Fatty Acid Extraction Using a Type V Deep Eutectic Solvent with Tunable Hydrophobicity. The Journal of Physical Chemistry B, 129(34), 8754-8763.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Deep eutectic solvents (DESs) are often promoted as a more environmentally friendly alternative for ionic liquids and other ionic solvents. Like ionic liquids, DESs can be designed for specific tasks in various chemical environments, but their usage in extraction processes is often significantly hampered by difficulties in recovering the extraction product. To remedy this, various tactics are being employed, which often decrease or completely remove the recyclability of the solvent. An experimental study from 2021 proposed a strategy to counter this issue, demonstrating how a hexanoic acid─imidazole (IMID) DES with “tunable hydrophobicity” can be used to extract fatty acids. This protocol did not involve the introduction of additional chemical species, thus better preserving the recyclability of the solvent. In this work, we reproduce the experimentally reported fatty acid extraction and recovery process using the coarse-grained Martini 3 force field. We demonstrate that our HexA-IMID DES simulations are capable of accurately reproducing the phase separation and extraction phenomena and yielding molecular level insights into the process. Additionally, we studied the effect of IL formation on these properties. Our study opens the way to rational design of new extraction protocols with DESs and further establishes the potential role CG MD can have in the screening of new DESs and their properties with comparatively little computational cost. Finally, we demonstrate that when combined with the Martini 3 IL models, we can efficiently study how different extents of reaction toward IL formation affect the system properties, as well as extraction properties.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Solvents</category>
  <category>Small molecules</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Vainikka2025_FattyAcidExtraction.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nanopore-Functionalized Hybrid Lipid-Block Copolymer Membranes Allow Efficient Single-Molecule Sampling and Stable Sensing of Human Serum</title>
  <dc:creator>Edo Vreeker, Fabian Grünewald, Nieck Jordy van der Heide, Andrea Bonini, Siewert J. Marrink, Katarzyna (Kasia) Tych, and Giovanni Maglia</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Vreeker2025_Nanopore.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Vreeker, E., Grünewald, F., van der Heide, N. J., Bonini, A., Marrink, S. J., Tych, K., &amp; Maglia, G. (2025). Nanopore‐Functionalized Hybrid Lipid‐Block Copolymer Membranes Allow Efficient Single‐Molecule Sampling and Stable Sensing of Human Serum. Advanced Materials, 2418462.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Biological nanopores are powerful tools for single-molecule detection, with promising potential as next-generation biosensors. A major bottleneck in nanopore analysis is the fragility of the supporting lipid membranes, that easily rupture after exposure to biological samples. Membranes comprising PMOXA-PDMS-PMOXA (poly(2-methyloxazoline-b-dimethylsiloxane-b-2-methyloxazoline)) or PBD-PEO (poly(1,2-butadiene)-b-poly(ethylene oxide)) polymers may form robust alternatives, but their suitability for the reconstitution of a broad range of nanopores has not yet been investigated. Here, PBD-PEO membranes are found to be highly robust toward applied voltages and human serum, while providing a poor environment for nanopore reconstitution. However, hybrid membranes containing a similar molar ratio of PBD11PEO8 polymers and diphytanoyl phosphatidylcholine (DPhPC) lipids show the best of both worlds: highly robust membranes suitable for the reconstitution of a wide variety of nanopores. Molecular dynamics simulations reveal that lipids form ≈12 nm domains interspersed by a polymer matrix. Nanopores partition into these lipid nanodomains and sequester lipids, possibly offering the same binding strength as in a native bilayer. Nanopores reconstituted in hybrid membranes yield efficient sampling of biomolecules and enable sensing of high concentrations of human serum. This work thus shows that hybrid membranes functionalized with nanopores allow single-molecule sensing, while forming robust interfaces, resolving an important bottleneck for novel nanopore-based biosensors.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Polymers</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Vreeker2025_Nanopore.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Peptide Electrostatic Modulation Directs Human Neural Cell Fate</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Perez-Chirinos, Xavier Barceló, M Gabriella Chiariello, Irene Sanz, Amaia Iturrospe, Arantxa Arbe, J Alberto Ortega, Siewert J Marrink, Aitziber L Cortajarena, Zaida Álvarez, and Ivan R Sasselli</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/PerezChirinos2025_PeptideModulation.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Perez‐Chirinos, L., Barceló, X., Chiariello, M. G., Sanz, I., Iturrospe, A., Arbe, A., … &amp; Sasselli, I. R. (2025). Peptide Electrostatic Modulation Directs Human Neural Cell Fate. Advanced Science, e07946.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Supramolecular self-assembled systems have emerged as versatile platforms for engineering biomimetic environments that precisely regulate cellular behavior. These materials have tunable properties such as stiffness, hydrophobicity, and molecular composition, allowing for customization of their structure and function. Despite significant advances, the specific role of electrostatic properties in modulating cellular responses within supramolecular assemblies remains poorly understood. Here, a peptide library with diverse electrostatic profiles is designed to systematically investigate their influence on the bioactivity of supramolecular assemblies for neural regeneration. Combining computational and experimental methods, the self-assembly conditions of these peptides are optimized to create stable, biologically relevant architectures. Using human neural progenitor cell (hNPC) cultures, it is demonstrated that negatively charged environments enhance cell survival and promote neuronal differentiation. Specifically, high negative charges activate critical signaling pathways, including the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) cascade and cell adhesion mechanisms, leading to neuronal lineage commitment. This study establishes a novel framework for the design of supramolecular systems, offering an unprecedented ability to analyze specific parameters in cell behavior. By achieving control beyond conventional biomaterials, this work provides valuable insights into the complex interplay of biophysical and biochemical cues in the native neural microenvironment, with implications for regenerative medicine and biomaterial design.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <category>Self-assembly</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/PerezChirinos2025_PeptideModulation.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Phase separation of protein kinase A regulatory subunits is driven by similar inter- and intra-molecular interactions involving the inhibitory segment</title>
  <dc:creator>Malyasree Giri, Christopher S Brasnett, Kubra F Eroglu, Julie Maiboll Kaasen, Alain AM Andre, Siewert-Jan Marrink, Frans AA Mulder, and Magnus Kjaergaard</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Giri2025_ProteinKinaseA.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Giri, M., Brasnett, C. S., Eroglu, K. F., Kaasen, J. M., Andre, A. A., Marrink, S. J., … &amp; Kjaergaard, M. (2025). Phase separation of protein kinase A regulatory subunits is driven by similar inter-and intra-molecular interactions involving the inhibitory segment. bioRxiv, 2025-08.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Phase separation of biological macromolecules has emerged as a widespread mechanism for cellular organization, governing the spatiotemporal regulation of biochemical processes including signaling pathways. The regulatory subunit of the cAMP-dependent protein kinase A (PKA) RIα phase separates following cAMP-induced kinase activation, thereby restricting and enhancing PKA activity in space and time. The N-terminal dimerization/docking (D/D) domain and the linker region of RIα have been identified as necessary and sufficient for phase separation, but their interactions at atomic resolution have remained elusive. We report here a structural investigation of the minimal phase-separating region of RIα by nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy (NMR) and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. The intrinsically disordered regions of RIα cause broadening of NMR signals throughout the protein indicative of widespread dynamic interactions. Mutation of arginine residues in the RIα inhibitory sequence leads to a reduction in signal broadening accompanied by loss of phase separation. Independently, binding of RIα to an A-kinase anchoring protein (AKAP) leads to spectral changes that are indicative of a loss of interactions between the D/D domain and the linker region, suggestive of a competition between intramolecular interactions and partner binding. Corroborating the experimental observations, multiscale MD simulations detect pervasive interactions of the folded D/D domain of RIα with the intrinsically disordered linker, and the intermolecular interactions in the condensate mirror those found internally in RIα dimers. Our results support the view that for PKA RIα, homotypic phase separation is underpinned by intermolecular interactions that are similar to intramolecular interactions.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Pre-print</category>
  <category>Biomolecular condensates</category>
  <category>Coacervate</category>
  <category>Multi-scale</category>
  <category>Proteins</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Giri2025_ProteinKinaseA.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TS2CG as a membrane builder</title>
  <dc:creator>Fabian Schuhmann, Jan A Stevens, Neda Rahmani, Isabell Lindahl, Chelsea M Brown, Christopher Brasnett, Dimitrios Anastasiou, Adrià Bravo Vidal, Beatrice J Geiger, Siewert J Marrink, and Weria Pezeshkian</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Schuhmann2025_TS2CG.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<!-- 
The info below is just an example. 

Both fields are required and they have to be replaced with the respective info for each paper. 

Please notice the `> ` symbol before the citation, it gives it additional styling.  
-->
<section id="citation-apa-7" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation-apa-7">Citation (APA 7)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Schuhmann, F., Stevens, J. A., Rahmani, N., Lindahl, I., Brown, C. M., Brasnett, C., … &amp; Pezeshkian, W. (2025). TS2CG as a membrane builder. Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation, 21(18), 9136-9146.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations excel at capturing biological processes at the molecular scale but rely on a well-defined initial structure. As MD simulations now extend to whole-cell-level modeling, new tools are needed to efficiently build initial structures. Here, we introduce TS2CG version 2, designed to construct coarse-grained membrane structures with any desired shape and lateral organization. This version enables precise placement of lipids and proteins based on curvature preference, facilitating the creation of large, near-equilibrium membranes. Additional features include controlled pore generation and the placement of specific lipids at membrane edges for stabilization. Moreover, a Python interface allows users to extend functionality while maintaining the high performance of the C++ core. To demonstrate its capabilities, we showcase challenging simulations, including a Möbius strip membrane, a vesicle with lipid domains as continental plates (Martini globe), and entire mitochondrial membranes exhibiting lipid heterogeneity due to curvature, along with a comprehensive set of tutorials.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Journal article</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Multi-scale</category>
  <category>Lipid membranes</category>
  <category>Vesicles</category>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/publications/entries/2025/Schuhmann2025_TS2CG.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
