<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Martini Force Field Initiative</title>
<link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/</link>
<atom:link href="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://cgmartini.nl/images/martini.gif</url>
<title>Martini Force Field Initiative</title>
<link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.7.31</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Martini workshop 2025 in Groningen</title>
  <dc:creator>SJ MARRINK</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-05-02-martini-workshop/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<!-- 
The text below is just an example. Please replace it with the actual description of the announcement. You can use markdown syntax to format the text.
-->
<p>Finally happening: another one of those famous Martini workshops !! From 11-15th of August, in the city of Groningen, The Netherlands. Learn from the Martini masters themselves. More info and registration details following soon.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-05-02-martini-workshop/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-05-02-martini-workshop/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini3-IDP</title>
  <dc:creator>Chris Brasnett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-03-24-martini3idp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Martini3-IDP is a new force field developed for applications to fully disordered and multidomain proteins, with detailed parameterisation and extensive validation against a range of reference systems. The force field and its features are both fully implemented in Martinize2 and Polyply for immediate use by the community.</p>
<p>For details, see <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-025-58199-2">Wang et al., Nature Communications (2025)</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-03-24-martini3idp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MartiniGlass</title>
  <dc:creator>Chris Brasnett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-03-26-martiniglass/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Integrating and optimising existing tools to visualise Martini systems in VMD, MartiniGlass is a new small Python package to rapidly generate visualisable topologies for your systems. The package may be particularly useful for inspecting your protein topology, or generating nice images with coarse grained beads linked - no more VDW drawing method necessary! MartiniGlass has full documentation and tutorials on its <a href="https://martiniglass.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">readthedocs site</a></p>
<p>For details, see <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jcim.4c02277">Brasnett and Marrink, JCIM (2025)</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-03-26-martiniglass/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2025-03-26-martiniglass/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="141" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martignac</title>
  <dc:creator>Siewert-Jan Marrink</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2024-12-18-martignac/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<!-- 
The text below is just an example. Please replace it with the actual description of the announcement. You can use markdown syntax to format the text.
-->
<p>The group of Bereau has developed computational workflows for reproducible, traceable, and composable Martini simulations, appropriately named ‘Martignac’. See https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jcim.4c01754 for details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2024-12-18-martignac/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Changes to Martinze2 options</title>
  <dc:creator>Chris Brasnett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2024-11-19-martinize-0-12-0/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As of Martinize2 version 0.12.0, the defaults of the <code>-scfix</code> and <code>-cys</code> flags have been changed.</p>
<p><code>-scfix</code> is now assumed by default, so it is no longer necessary to specify it. If you do, a warning will be raised. If you purposefully intend to generate protein models without side chain fixes, the <code>-noscfix</code> flag can be used.</p>
<p>Additionally, the default argument of <code>-cys</code> is changed to <code>auto</code> to search for disulfide bridges in your topology by default, so no longer needs to be explicitly specified unless you want to turn off the behaviour (<code>-cys none</code>) or specify the search distance for disulfide bridges manually (e.g.&nbsp;<code>-cys 5</code> will enforce disulfide bridges between cysteines within 5 nm of each other).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2024-11-19-martinize-0-12-0/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhD/Post doc positions</title>
  <dc:creator>Chelsea Brown (on behalf of Siewert-Jan Marrink)</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2024-11-11-groningen-positions/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<!-- 
The text below is just an example. Please replace it with the actual description of the announcement. You can use markdown syntax to format the text.
-->
<p>Building a synthetic cell is one of the greatest scientific and technological challenges of the 21st century. In the framework of a huge national Dutch program (<a href="https://www.evolf.life">EVOLF</a>) and a European Doctorate network (<a href="https://www.comeincell.org">ComeInCell</a>), we have 12 PhD/Postdoc positions available for biophysicists, bioengineers, biochemists, and molecular biologist at the <a href="https://www.rug.nl/research/gbb">Groningen Biomolecular Sciences and Biotechnology Institute</a> of the University of Groningen in the Netherlands.</p>
<p><strong>Marrink group </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Position 11: Multiscale modeling of cell division, probing the interplay between lipids and proteins for the rational design of efficient fission of artificial cells. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-16094-y">Further reading</a></li>
<li>Position 12: Molecular dynamics simulations of minimal cells, focusing on the properties and organization of the cell envelope. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2023.1106495">Further reading</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Closing date 1/12/2024</strong></p>
<p>Read more here: <a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12830433/12-phd-post-doc-positions-for-the-design-and-engineering-of-synthetic-cells-/">Nature careers</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2024-11-11-groningen-positions/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Membrane buckling artefact</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Ramirez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-07-25-membrane-buckling-artifact/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In MD simulations using the GROMACS package with default Martini parameters, the group of Hummer found large membranes to deform under the action of a semi-isotropically coupled barostat. As the primary cause, they identified overly short outer cutoffs and infrequent neighbor list updates that result in missed long-range attractive Lennard-Jones interactions. Small but systematic imbalances in the apparent pressure tensor then induce unphysical asymmetric box deformations that crumple the membrane. Guidelines are presented to avoid these artefacts, including estimates for appropriate values for the outer cutoff r_l and the number of time steps nstlist between neighbor list updates.</p>
<p>Must-read for those who simulate membrane systems. For details, see the paper from <a href="https://chemrxiv.org/engage/chemrxiv/article-details/64b55faeb053dad33a692084">Kim et al.&nbsp;in chemRxiv</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-07-25-membrane-buckling-artifact/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini in OpenMM</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Ramirez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-04-13-martini_openmm/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The group of Tieleman has completed an implementation of Martini 2 and Martini 3 in the OpenMM molecular dynamics software package. OpenMM is a flexible molecular dynamics package widely used for methods development and is competitive in speed on GPUs with other commonly used packages. OpenMM has facilities to easily implement new force field terms, external forces and fields, and other non-standard features, which were used to implement all force field terms of Martini 2 and Martini 3. This allows OpenMM simulations, starting with GROMACS topology files that are processed by custom scripts, with all the added flexibility of OpenMM. For details, see the paper of <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2023.04.007">MacCallum et al., Biophys J., 2023</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-04-13-martini_openmm/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SARS-COV2 envelope</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Ramirez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-04-07-sars-cov2-env/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Finally our integrative model of SARS-Cov-2 is published, representing the most realistic model of this viral envelope to date, with interesting pattern formation of the M-dimers.</p>
<p>For details, see <a href="https://authors.elsevier.com/c/1ghE13SNvc6nDG">Pezeshkian et al., Structure (2023)</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-04-07-sars-cov2-env/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-04-07-sars-cov2-env/image.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ubiquitination driving ER protein complexation</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Ramirez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-06-06-ubiquitination/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The computational cell biology group of Ramachandra Bhaskara has used MARTINI models of Ubiquitinated RHD proteins to show volume exclusion and non-specific Ub-Ub interactions driving the formation of homomeric and heteromeric complexes on ER membranes boosting selective-ER phagy. The computation-based findings are supported by super-resolution imaging and in vitro membrane remodeling assays apart from cell biology experiments. Published in TWO (!) Nature papers:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>González, A., Covarrubias-Pinto, A., Bhaskara, R. M., Glogger, M., Kuncha, S. K., Xavier, A., Seemann, E., Misra, M., Hoffmann, M. E., Bräuning, B., Balakrishnan, A., Qualmann, B., Dötsch, V., Schulman, B. A., Kessels, M. M., Hübner, C. A., Heilemann, M., Hummer, G., &amp; Dikić, I. (2023). Ubiquitination regulates ER-phagy and remodelling of endoplasmic reticulum. Nature, 1-8. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06089-2">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06089-2</a></p></li>
<li><p>Foronda, H., Fu, Y., Covarrubias-Pinto, A., Bocker, H. T., González, A., Seemann, E., Franzka, P., Bock, A., Bhaskara, R. M., Liebmann, L., Hoffmann, M. E., Katona, I., Koch, N., Weis, J., Kurth, I., Gleeson, J. G., Reggiori, F., Hummer, G., Kessels, M. M., Qualmann, B., . . . Hübner, C. A. (2023). Heteromeric clusters of ubiquitinated ER-shaping proteins drive ER-phagy. Nature, 1-9. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06090-9">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06090-9</a></p></li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-06-06-ubiquitination/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-06-06-ubiquitination/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="99" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reactive Martini</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Ramirez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-06-17-reactive-martini/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>See the paper by Selim Sami, explaining a pragmatic way to capture chemical reactivity in Martini with the clever use of virtual sites: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.2c01186">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.2c01186</a>.</p>
<p>All the required input files together with tutorials on its use are provided as SI.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-06-17-reactive-martini/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martini 3 LPS</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Ramirez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-09-15-martini3-LPS/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>See the paper from Vaiwala and Ayappa, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.3c00471">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.3c00471</a>. Parameters can be found in the SI of their paper.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://cgmartini.nl/docs/announcements/posts/2023-09-15-martini3-LPS/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
